A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Reports, 1970-2014
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
University of Virginia School of Medicine Reports, 1970-2014
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-66
10 boxes measuring 5.5 inches x 10 inches x 15.5 inches and 11 boxes measuring 5 inches x 10 inches x 15.5 inches; total of 9.25 linear feet
University of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions
Acquisition Information
The documents in boxes 1-19, folder 7 arrived at the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library in several installments from the School of Medicine prior to 2014. On December 2, 2014, Addeane Caelleigh, a Medical Education Case Writer at the School of Medicine, brought the materials in boxes 19, folder 8 through 21, folder 2 to Historical Collections.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 104 folders of processed material. Series I contains annual reports of the School of Medicine from the 1970s and then biennial reports through the 1980s with a planning report that looks forward to 2000. The reports come from the various departments and divisions within the School of Medicine. Series II has only two documents concerning the development of biostatistics and epidemiology as well as a Family Medicine residency in Lynchburg. Series III includes documents on the methods taken to increase the number of minority medical students as well as minority faculty. One document concerns the entire university. Series IV has documents, reports, studies, questionnaire summaries, and data from self-studies. Self-studies were done for the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, and in some cases those documents relate to the entire University with only sections that concern the School of Medicine. Other self-studies were done for the Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) which represented the American Medical Association and the Association of American Medical Colleges. Documents in the collection are instructional in terms of how to prepare for the LCME site visits as well as documents submitted prior to the visits. Liaison Committee on Medical Education visits for reaccreditation occurred on October 11-15, 1998, October 8-11, 2006, and October 19-22, 2014.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in four series with the documents within each series arranged chronologically. The series are:
Series I, School of Medicine Annual Reports and Biennial Reports, 1970-1990
Series II, School of Medicine Proposals, 1977-1982
Series III, School of Medicine Reports on Minority Affairs, 1984-1991
Series IV, School of Medicine Self-Study Reports, 1974-2014
Contents List
- Series I: School of Medicine Annual Reports and Biennial Reports 1970-1989
  The annual reports contain individual reports from departments or divisions. The departmental reports include information about the faculty in terms of research, scholarly recognition of faculty, professional committees or offices held, publications, highlights or summary of the year, general considerations, changes in curriculum, and problem areas.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, 1970 (Box-folder 1:1)
    The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Clinical Pathology, Dermatology, Internal Medicine, Microbiology, Neurological Surgery, Neurology, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, and Urology. Internal Medicine was formally organized during the course of the year with the establishment of 12 divisions: Biometrics, Cardiology, Clinical Pharmacology, Endocrinology and Metabolism, Epidemiology and Virology, Gastroenterology, Hematology, Infectious Diseases, Nephrology, Oncology, Pulmonary-Allergy, and Rheumatology. Ten medical students were dropped for academic deficiencies during 1969-1970.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, 1971 (Box-folder 1:2)
    The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dermatology, Internal Medicine, Medical Library, Microbiology, Neurology, Neurological Surgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, Urology, and Vivarium. No students were dropped for academic deficiencies. Special recruitment was done by the Admissions Committee and faculty who visited 13 colleges with predominantly black enrollment.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2:1)
    The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dermatology, Internal Medicine, Medical Library, Microbiology, Neurosurgery, Neurology, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Student Health, Surgery, Urology, Vivarium, and Equal Opportunity Program. The report from the Equal Opportunity Program includes selection of new faculty and non-academic personnel of those underrepresented in the school. Specifically mentioned are women, black, Chicanos, Orientals, and Chinese.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Section I, Academic Affairs (Part I), 1973-1975 (Box-folder 3:1)
    The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dentistry, Dermatology, Family Medicine, Internal Medicine, Health Sciences Library, and Microbiology. At the front of the report is the School of Medicine Annual Report, 1973-74 and 1974-75, Part II Academic Affairs, Section III Dean’s Summary and Recommendations. It states that due to new pressures and the need for better organization in the School of Medicine, and in response to University–wide programs, several tasks were completed by faculty. Some of these are included in the report including the identification and adoption of institutional goals, a report on plans and projections, a financial report to the President, and a preliminary policy report on promotions and tenure. The dean’s summary gives information on a variety of topics, but of note is the formation of the Department of Family Practice on July 1, 1975 and a Division of Dentistry in 1974, the completion of the new Health Sciences Library, an award toward the construction of a Primary Care Building, and an experimental or alternative curriculum for the School of Medicine.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Section I, Academic Affairs (Part II), 1973-1975 (Box-folder 4:1)
    The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Neurosurgery, Neurology, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Student Health, Surgery, and Urology.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Section II, Equal Opportunity Programs, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 4:2)
    The departments filled out reports addressing the selection of new faculty, the selection and promotion of non-academic personnel, and special efforts.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Section A, (Part I), 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5:1)
    The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dentistry, Dermatology, Family Practice, Internal Medicine, Health Sciences Library, and Microbiology.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Department of Medicine, 1975 September 1 – 1976 August 31 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Section A (Part II), 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Part C: Academic Planning, 1975 September 1 - 1976 September 1 (Box-folder 6:1)
    The annual report includes a letter of request, summary of requests for faculty and space, and a one year extension of academic plan for the Departments of: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dentistry, Dermatology, Family Practice, Internal Medicine, Microbiology, Neurology, Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, Urology, and Western State Hospital.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Dean’s Summary 1976 August 31 - 1977 August 31 (Box-folder 6:2)
    The Dean’s Summary includes Medical School Administration; Improving the Academic Environment for Students; Summary of Major Accomplishments in Instruction, Research, and Public Service; Summary of Major Modifications in Academic Programs, 1978-79; Major space considerations, 1978-79; Memorandum to Departments regarding Annual Report. Norman J. Knorr is the School of Medicine Dean.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Part III, (Book 1), 1976 August 31 - 1977 August 31 (Box-folder 6:3)
    The annual report contains reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Dermatology, Dentistry, Family Practice, Internal Medicine, Microbiology, Neurology, and Neurosurgery.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Part III, (Book 2), 1976 August 31 - 1977 August 31 (Box-folder 6:4)
    The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Obstetrics and Gynecology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, Urology, and Roanoke.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, 1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31 (Box-folder 7:1)
    The annual report includes a “Summary of Major Accomplishments in Instruction, Research, and Public Service” which highlights a few of the major accomplishments of the individual departments. Dean Norman Knorr mentions a major revision of the preclinical curriculum by the council on Medical Education and a new Division of Geriatrics under the leadership of Richard Lindsay with the anticipation of a special geriatric unit to be established at the Blue Ridge Sanatorium in the future. Currently there are established programs in epilepsy and outpatient Psychiatry at Blue Ridge. Another new Division is Geographic Medicine under the direction of Richard Guerrant. There is a report from the Office of Student Affairs and a break-down of SOM admissions.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Anatomy – Dentistry, 1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31 (Box-folder 7:2)
    The annual report contains the reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, and Dentistry.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Dermatology – Neurology, 1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31 (Box-folder 7:3)
    The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Dermatology, Family Practice, Internal Medicine, Microbiology, and Neurology.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Neurosurgery – Plastic Surgery, 1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31 (Box-folder 7:4)
    The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, and Plastic Surgery.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Psychiatry – Roanoke Program, 1977 September 1 - 1978 August 31 (Box-folder 8:1)
    The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, Urology, Roanoke Program.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, 1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31 (Box-folder 8:2)
    A memo inserted in front of the 1978-1979 Annual Report from Dean Norman Knorr, dated September 14, 1981, indicates that the School of Medicine Biennial Report (formerly Annual Report) is waived this year as the plan is to submit the Self-Study Report in its place. The 1978-1979 annual report includes a “Summary of Major Accomplishments in Teaching Programs, Research Programs, and Public Service Activities” and a report from the Office of Student Affairs.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Anatomy – Biomedical Engineering, 1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31 (Box-folder 8:3)
    The annual report contains the reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Biochemistry, and Biomedical Engineering.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Dermatology – Microbiology, 1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31 (Box-folder 8:4)
    The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Dermatology, Dentistry, Family Practice, Internal Medicine, and Microbiology.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Neurology – Roanoke, 1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31 (Box-folder 9:1)
    The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Neurology, Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Radiology, Surgery, Urology, and Roanoke Program.
  - School of Medicine Annual Report, Pediatrics, 1978 September 1 - 1979 August 31 (Box-folder 9:2)
    The annual report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Pediatrics.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Summary, 1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1 (Box-folder 10:1)
    This summary of the biennial report highlights a few of the accomplishments in teaching programs, training programs, clinical service programs, research programs, and public service activities. The School of Medicine did a self-study in preparation for the LCME accreditation site visit held in February 1982. The LCME conferred full accreditation of the program for 10 years. A new graduate program in Cell and Molecular Biology was established in 1982 and a number of new divisions were formed. New units opened at Blue Ridge Hospital and a Travelers Clinic and the Blue Ridge Poison Control Center were established at the University Hospital. UVa Medcial Center was designated a Level I Trauma Center in 1982. James W. Craig submitted a report from the Office of Student Affairs.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Anatomy – Family Medicine, 1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1 (Box-folder 10:2)
    The report contains the reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Biomedical Engineering, Comparative Medicine, Dermatology, and Family Medicine.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Internal Medicine, 1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1 (Box-folder 10:3)
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Microbiology - Pathology, 1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1 (Box-folder 11:1)
    The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Microbiology, Neurology, Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ophthalmology, Orthopaedics, Otolaryngology, and Pathology.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Pediatrics - Urology, 1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1 (Box-folder 11:2)
    The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Behavior Medicine and Psychiatry, Radiology, Surgery, and Urology.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Curriculum Vitae, 1981 June 30 – 1983 July 1 (Box-folder 12:1)
    The CVs are arranged alphabetically, but seem to be missing the beginning as the first name is Dickerson.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Anatomy – Biomedical Engineering, 1982 July 1 – 1984 June 31 (Box-folder 12:2)
    The report contains the reports from individual departments or divisions: Anatomy, Anesthesiology, Behavior Medicine and Psychiatry, Biochemistry, and Biomedical Engineering
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Comparative Medicine – Internal Medicine, 1982 July 1 – 1984 June 31 (Box-folder 13:1)
    The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Comparative Medicine, Dentistry, Family Medicine, and Internal Medicine.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Microbiology - Pathology, 1982 July 1 – 1984 June 31 (Box-folder 13:2)
  - School of Medicine Biennial Report, Pediatrics - Urology, 1982 July 1 – 1984 June 31 (Box-folder 14:1)
    The report continues the reports from individual departments or divisions: Pediatrics, Pharmacology, Physiology, Plastic Surgery, Radiology, Surgery, and Urology.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Anesthesiology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 14:2)
    The report is from Robert M. Epstein, Chair of the Department of Anesthesiology.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Behavioral Medicine & Psychiatry, Volume I, (W.W. Spradlin, Chair), 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 14:3)
    The report is from W.W. Spradlin, Chair of the Department of Behavioral Medicine & Psychiatry.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Behavioral Medicine & Psychiatry, Volume II, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 14:4)
    The report is from W.W. Spradlin, Chair of the Department of Behavioral Medicine & Psychiatry which includes second-year course materials.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Anatomy & Cell Biology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:1)
    The report is from the Department of Anatomy & Cell Biology prepared by Charles J. Flickinger.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Biochemistry, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:2)
    The report is from the Department Biochemistry.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Biomedical Engineering, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:3)
    The report is from the Department of Biomedical Engineering.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Central Electron Microscope Facility, 1986 October (Box-folder 15:4)
    The planning report is for 1988-1998 from Charles J. Flickinger regarding the Central Electron Microscope Facility.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Comparative Medicine, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:5)
    The report is from the Department of Comparative Medicine.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Dentistry, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:6)
    The report is from Byard S. Deputy, Chair of the Department of Dentistry and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Dermatology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:7)
    The report is from the Department of Dermatology and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Fluorescent Activated Cell Sorter (FACS) Laboratory, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:8)
    The planning report is for the Fluorescent Activated Cell Sorter Laboratory for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Lymphocyte Culture Center, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:9)
    The planning report is from John C. Herr for the Lymphocyte Culture Center for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Medicine, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:10)
    The report is from Edward W. Hook, Chair of the Department of Medicine, and includes detailed reports from each of the 16 divisions of the Department with planning reports for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Microbiology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:11)
    The report is from the Department of Microbiology and includes short term objectives for 1986-1988.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Neurological Surgery, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 15:12)
    The report is from John A. Jane of the Department of Neurosurgery and includes objectives for 1986-1988 by John A. Persing.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Neurology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:1)
    The report is from T. J. Johns, Chair of the Department of Neurology and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Neuroscience, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:2)
    The report states that the Department of Neuroscience was established in the SOM by the Board of Visitors in 1985. It includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:3)
    The report for the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Ophthalmology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:4)
    The report is from Brian P. Conway, Chair of the Department of Ophthalmology and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:5)
    The report for Orthopaedic Surgery and Rehabilitation is dated 1982-1984.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Otolaryngology – Head and Neck Surgery, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:6)
    The report for Otolaryngology – Head and Neck Surgery includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Pathology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:7)
    The report is from Thomas W. Tillack, Chair of the Department of Pathology, and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Pediatrics, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:8)
    The report is from Robert M. Blizzard, Chair of the Department of Pediatrics, and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Pharmacology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:9)
    The report is from the Department of Pharmacology and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Physiology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:10)
    The report is from the Department of Physiology and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Department of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:11)
    The report is from Gaylord S. Williams in Dr. Edgerton’s absence from the Department of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Protein and Nucleic Acid Research Facility, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:12)
    The report is from the Protein and Nucleic Acid Research Facility and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Radiology, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:13)
    The report is from T. E. Keats, Chair of the Department of Radiology, and includes a planning report for 1988-1998.
  - School of Medicine Biennial Evaluation and Planning Report, Surgery, 1984 July 1 – 1986 June 30 (Box-folder 16:14)